Guide to the William B. Davis Papers, 1892 - 1940
William B. Davis Papers, 1892 - 1940
Special Collections & Archives, Wesleyan University
Davis, William B.
1000-150
0.5
1
William Butler Davis (1871-1937) was a graduate of the Wesleyan University class of 1894 and a musician. He served as a choirmaster, organist, and music teacher in Connecticut during his career.
The William B. Davis Papers consist mostly sheet music hand-written by William Butler Davis, Wesleyan class of 1894 and composer of the Wesleyan alma mater, Come Raise the Song. Davis composed what he referred to as a light opera called The Girl and the Graduate. The piano, vocal, and orchestral sheet music is included in this collection, as well as some other pieces Davis composed. He was a member of the Glee Club while at Wesleyan and he kept a scrapbook of Glee Club programs and news clippings that mentioned himself or the Glee Club from 1892 to 1895.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
No restrictions.
Acquisitions Information
Acquired prior to 1980.
Biographical Note
William Butler Davis was born in Middletown, Connecticut, on September 27, 1871 and died on November 16, 1937, in Old Saybrook, Connecticut. He attended Wesleyan University where he earned his bachelor of philosophy in 1894. He then attended Trinity College where he earned his bachelor of music degree in 1918. Most of his life was focused on music: from 1894 to 1927, Davis was the choirmaster and organist of The Church of the Holy Trinity in Middletown; from 1908 to 1928, director of the Glee Club; from 1892 to 1917, an instructor in church music at the Berkeley Divinity School of Yale University; and in 1917, he was the music instructor at Middletown High School. In 1907, Davis along with fellow Wesleyan alumnus, Kenneth Goode, class of 1904, wrote a comic opera called The Girl and the Graduate. It was first performed locally in 1907 and later performed at the Berkley Theater in New York City to a standing-room only audience. Davis never married, but he was very involved in his teaching, especially while teaching at Middletown High School, where each year, he would chose two students whom he would sponsor for four years at Wesleyan. In 1928, Davis moved out of Middletown to Old Saybrook, but continued to teach at Middletown High School until he died.
Collection Overview
The William B. Davis Papers consist mostly sheet music hand-written by William Butler Davis, Wesleyan class of 1894 and composer of the Wesleyan alma mater, Come Raise the Song. Davis composed what he referred to as a light opera called The Girl and the Graduate. The piano, vocal, and orchestral sheet music is included in this collection, as well as some other pieces Davis composed. He was a member of the Glee Club while at Wesleyan and he kept a scrapbook of Glee Club programs and news clippings that mentioned himself or the Glee Club from 1892 to 1895.
Online Catalog Headings
These and related materials may be found under the following headings in online catalogs.
Davis, William B.; Wesleyan University (Middletown, Conn.)--Alumni and alumnae.; Wesleyan University (Middletown, Conn.)--Students.; Choruses, Secular (Men’s voices), Unaccompanied.
Detailed Description of the Collection
  - Scrapbook (Scrapbook 1)
    - Concerts of Wesleyan Programmes
    - Glee Club and concerts in which Billy B. Davis sang, 1894
    - Press Notices of Wesleyan Glee Club and of Billy B. Davis, Baritone, 1892-1895
  - Wesleyan Songs by W.B. Davis, 1894 (Box 1)
    Small book.
  - William Butler Davis, major life accomplishments
  - Come Raise the Song (alma mater), 1894 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - To Glee Club (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - The Girl and the Graduate (Box 1, Folder 2)
    2 copies.
  - The Girl and the Graduate programs, 1908, 1912, 1931 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Article about The Girl and the Graduate in the Wesleyan Argus, Vol. XLI-No. 22, April 8, 1908 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - The Girl and the Graduate sheet music (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Those Girls (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - $20,000,000 Song (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Sheet Music (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Unknown, 1907 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Ave Verum Corpus Natum (Jesu hand of God incarnate), undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - My Heart if a Dandy Lion Blossom, undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Jesu, the very thought of Thee, 1914 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Here's a Health to Wesleiana, 1916 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Hail Wesleiana, a chorus of Praise, undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Pilgrim's Song (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - In the bleak mid-winter, 1932, 1935, undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Wesleyan Compline Song, 1917 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - The Alma Mater Has Been Improved, by Wm. B. Davis, The Wesleyan University Alumnus, 1934 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Wesleyan University Department of Music memo, 1940 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Brother Omega, 1916 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Seven Well-Known Hymns with Original Tunes, undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - The Girl and the Graduate
    - Printed sheet music, 1908: Home is Where the Heart is (Box 1, Folder 7)
      3 copies.
    - Printed sheet music, 1908: Collection of songs (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Act I sheet music (piano and vocal, with script in between songs) (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Act I: Those Girls (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Act I: Proposal Song (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Finale - Act I (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Overture (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Act I piano and vocal score (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - When a Girl's in Love (piano and vocal) (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - A Change in the Times (piano and vocal) (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Act II sheet music (piano and vocal, with script in between songs) (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Act II piano and vocal sheet music (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Overture orchestra parts (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Those Girls orchestra parts (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - $20,000,000 Song orchestra parts (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - McSwatt's entrance song orchestra parts (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - A Change in the Times orchestra parts (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Proposal Song orchestra parts (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - In Thibet orchestra parts (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Finale Act I orchestra parts (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Home is Where the Heart is (Act II opening chorus) orchestra parts (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - When a Girl's in Love orchestra parts (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - Entrance of the Thibetians orchestra parts (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - Sometimes orchestra parts (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - Finale Act II orchestra parts (Box 1, Folder 25)
      2 sets.